<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >

]>

<publicwhip scrapeversion="/home/twfy-live/parldata/scrapedxml/debates/debates2022-09-10b.xml" latest="no">
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.653.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.653.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.653.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.653.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.654.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.654.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.654.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.654.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.654.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.654.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.655.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.655.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.655.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.655.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.655.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.655.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.656.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.656.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.657.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.657.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.658.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.658.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.658.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.658.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.659.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.659.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.659.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.659.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.660.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.660.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.661.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.661.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.662.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.662.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.663.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.663.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.663.0" speakername="Stephen Timms" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10596" colnum="663" time="13:47:00" url="">
    <p pid="b663.0/1">Like other Members, my main memories of Her late Majesty the Queen are of visits to my constituency. In 1987, I was chair of Newham Council’s planning committee, and I negotiated with Mowlem the terms of its planning permission for London City airport. I attended the opening by Her Majesty in November 1987. It was pointed out that the terminal at the airport was on the site where her grandfather opened the King George V dock in 1921, 66 years before.</p>
    <p pid="b663.0/2">The airport was controversial locally. It turned out that most local residents, still smarting from the economic damage of the docks’ closure 10 years earlier, welcomed the jobs it was bringing, but some were very unhappy, understandably, about living with the noise of the planes. On the day of the airport opening, there was a small demonstration. The airport management, rightly wanting to avoid unnecessary ill feeling, invited half a dozen demonstrators inside and gave them a chance to meet the Queen and set out their case. When it came to their turn, the residents explained their fears about aircraft noise. The Queen listened carefully to what they had to say and replied, “I know exactly what you mean. You should hear the noise at Windsor castle of the jets coming in to land at Heathrow.”</p>
    <p pid="b663.0/3">The Prime Minister said yesterday that Her late Majesty had a unique ability to transcend difference and heal division. That is what she did on that occasion. Her off-the-cuff response transformed the situation. Arriving as disgruntled outsiders, the residents had been transformed into insiders who had shared a moment of recognition and warmth with their head of state. The rancour between the objectors and the airport was, I think, permanently eased.</p>
    <p pid="b663.0/4">The day after the opening ceremony for London 2012, which was a Saturday, when we might have thought that after the night before the then 86-year-old monarch would have been entitled to a day off, the Queen returned to London City airport to mark its 25th anniversary. Other memorable visits included, in her Golden Jubilee tour, a visit to Green Street, the most successful Asian shopping street in the country—we claim—where she was greeted by enthusiastic women in colourful saris waving Union Jacks, creating wonderful photographs in the Daily Mail the next day.</p>
    <p pid="b663.0/5">We always remember the Queen opening what we now call Newham University Hospital in December 1983. Her reign was seven decades: those treasured memories will last for many decades more.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.663.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.663.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.664.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.664.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.665.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.665.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.666.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.666.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.667.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.667.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.667.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.667.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.668.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.668.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.668.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.668.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.669.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.669.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.669.0" speakername="Harriett Baldwin" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/24785" colnum="669" time="14:13:00" url="">
    <p pid="b669.0/1">It is with great humility and sadness that I rise to pay tribute to Her late Majesty the Queen on behalf of my constituents in West Worcestershire. When we think of the sadness that we are feeling, we can only imagine how much grief her family members must be feeling, and we send them our heartfelt condolences. I think so many of us had hoped that Her late Majesty would reach her 100th birthday, like her mother, and that she would have to decide whether to send herself a telegram.</p>
    <p pid="b669.0/2">During her reign, Her late Majesty made four official visits to Worcestershire, most recently during her diamond jubilee tour, when she opened her faithful city of Worcester’s new library, The Hive. It was an honour to meet her on that occasion. On her first visit to Worcestershire as Queen, in 1957, she came to Malvern to see the Royal Radar Establishment and Malvern College. Radar was invented in Malvern and it played such an important role in our winning the second world war.</p>
    <p pid="b669.0/3">As many colleagues have said, Her late Majesty took a particular interest in our work here in Parliament. She invited all new MPs to meet her after the election in 2010. It was on that occasion that I learned of her fondness for Malvern water. It was on that occasion that I learned of her fondness for Malvern water. Since then, many of us have always thought that it was perhaps Malvern water that had given Her Majesty her wonderful complexion and helped her enjoy such a long life.</p>
    <p pid="b669.0/4">Many tributes have made it clear how close the Queen’s relationship has been with this Parliament, but as Chair of the British group in the Inter-Parliamentary Union, I wish to highlight her role in supporting international parliamentary democracy, human rights and the rule of law around the world. The Inter-Parliamentary Union brings together almost the whole of the world’s parliamentarians, and as our Head of State, the Queen opened three of the organisation’s conferences in London—those in 1957 and 1975 and, notably, the centenary conference of the IPU in 1989. As she addressed those hundreds of parliamentarians from around the world, she underlined the core values of multilateralism and the importance of bringing parliamentarians together to find peaceful methods of solving disputes and to understand each other. In this time of grieving, let us reinforce that wisdom that lasting peace must come through words.</p>
    <p pid="b669.0/5">Our late Queen is now at peace and, in the words of our daily prayer in this Chamber, may she attain everlasting joy and felicity. God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.670.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.670.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.671.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.671.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.671.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.671.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.672.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.672.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.673.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.673.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.673.0" speakername="Wes Streeting" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25320" colnum="673" time="14:27:00" url="">
    <p pid="b673.0/1">It is a privilege to follow so many others in rising to pay tribute to her late Majesty the Queen on behalf of the people of Ilford North and the London Borough of Redbridge. The depth of our sorrow reflects—in part—the length of her reign, her lifetime of service and duty, and the devotion she gave to her family, our country and our Commonwealth, but it also reflects how special the woman beneath the Crown was: at once the head of our royal family and yet able to touch the hearts of every family in the land.</p>
    <p pid="b673.0/2">East London holds a special place in its heart for the royal family. During the second world war, King George VI and his family stayed in London during the blitz and visited families whose lives and livelihoods had been devastated by the Nazi onslaught. The then Princess Elizabeth visited Ilford to see those affected by the bombing the day after VE Day in 1945 and returned again in 1949 to see the one thousandth council home that had been built by Atlee’s Government. She is said to have remarked,</p>
    <p pid="b673.0/3" class="indent" pwmotiontext="yes">“of all the houses and estates I have visited, Ilford’s are the best”.</p>
    <p pid="b673.0/4">She also visited a care home where one elderly resident was so thrilled to meet the Princess that they immediately burst into tears of happiness.</p>
    <p pid="b673.0/5">I saw a similar outpouring of emotion when the Queen visited Ilford again for her diamond jubilee in 2012, where she unveiled a plaque to the dry garden created in her honour in Valentines Park. It spoke to the great challenge of climate change—a cause close to the heart of our dear King. One resident told the Ilford Recorder,</p>
    <p pid="b673.0/6">“we have always read about queens and princesses in the story books. To have the Queen in our neighbourhood, it’s like a dream come true.”</p>
    <p pid="b673.0/7">A dream come true—that is a sentiment I cannot imagine being elicited for a mere President, and one that was certainly elicited with no effort for Her Majesty the Queen. It hardly seems real that that dream has ended.</p>
    <p pid="b673.0/8">We are privileged to have lived in the second Elizabethan age. Her late Majesty the Queen oversaw our country’s transition from empire to Commonwealth, to a modern democracy, witnessing huge social changes throughout her lifetime. So many of my constituents are proud of those changes, and of course retain strong familial bonds across the Commonwealth. Her Majesty showed by example that tradition and modernity are not adversaries but well-suited companions, from her first televised address to her very last Zoom call. From the beginning of her reign, amid rationing and post-war reconstruction, to her address to the nation at the height of the covid pandemic, she reminded us that whatever the triumphs and disasters of our history, our country’s best days now lie ahead. History, like life, moves on.</p>
    <p pid="b673.0/9">His Majesty the King has told us that the grief of the nation, and indeed the grief of the world, has provided comfort to his family for their irreparable loss. I hope he knows that his presence in our lives in recent days has been comforting and reassuring too—and if I may say so, Mr Speaker, when the Queen welcomed the then Duchess of Cornwall into her family, the nation took her into our hearts. It is a privilege and a pleasure to see her take her place as Queen Consort.</p>
    <p pid="b673.0/10">We are blessed to have known the reign of Elizabeth II, our greatest Queen. May God rest her soul, and may God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.674.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.674.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.674.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.674.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.674.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.674.2" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.674.2" speakername="Nick Smith" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/24728" colnum="674" time="14:32:00" url="">
    <p pid="b674.2/1">I mourn the passing of Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II, and on behalf of my constituents, I offer my heartfelt condolences to the royal family.</p>
    <p pid="b674.2/2">When I heard the sad news, my first thought was that we, the British people, had lost our pre-eminent public servant. Her late Majesty once said:</p>
    <p pid="b674.2/3" class="indent" pwmotiontext="yes">“I do not give you laws or administer justice, but I can do something else. I can give you my heart and devotion to these old islands and to all the peoples of our brotherhood of nations.”</p>
    <p pid="b674.2/4">Queen Elizabeth dedicated her life to the greater good, and wove together the ties that bind us.</p>
    <p pid="b674.2/5">In 2012 the Queen visited Ebbw Vale. It was one of those days in our valleys when the skies empty gallons, but still she saw through the programme. Her late Majesty knew that meeting our community leaders, hearing our choirs, collecting flowers from children—being with us—mattered. She showered good will on the people of Blaenau Gwent as the water rained down on all of us.</p>
    <p pid="b674.2/6">In the days that followed, the Queen also visited Aberfan. She was due to open a new school in the village that had been struck by grief just 46 years earlier. On reflection, I now realise that she was the constant. She was there when tragedy struck, standing alongside us when our nation mourned, but she was also there to usher in the new beginnings.</p>
    <p pid="b674.2/7">As I look to the future and think of His Majesty King Charles III, I recall his visit, as Prince of Wales, to Ysbyty Aneurin Bevan, the hospital named after my predecessor who established our national health service. Although it was very carefully done, there was a nod to the political genius who established yet another great institution of our country. The Prince wore a blue cornflower in his buttonhole—it was a classy look. He clearly knew of our great valleys and their history. I have no doubt that he will continue the legacy of his beloved mother, the late Queen.</p>
    <p pid="b674.2/8">Finally, I warmly welcome the naming of the new Prince and Princess of Wales. Though I mourn our longest-reigning monarch, I now say, God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.675.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.675.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.676.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.676.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.677.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.677.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.677.0" speakername="Kelly Tolhurst" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25430" colnum="677" time="14:43:00" url="">
    <p pid="b677.0/1">I rise on behalf of my constituents in Rochester and Strood to extend my deepest condolences to the royal family. Her late Majesty’s death is a terrible loss for us all and has touched every corner of the world. She was a constant reassuring presence. The world is unrecognisable from the start of her reign but, despite those changes, she was a steadying figure who led this country from the aftermath of the second world war to being the country that we are today.</p>
    <p pid="b677.0/2">Like many in the House, I had only lived under the Queen’s reign. As a female born in 1978, I was lucky to be born into a unique era for this country and grow up under both a female Head of State and a female Prime Minister for the first time in history. We had those powerful female figures at the top of our country, so for me it was absolutely normal to see women leading.</p>
    <p pid="b677.0/3">The Queen was a remarkable figure and an inspiration to many, whose influence has shaped generations as the values that she embodied of a sense of duty, public service and quiet dignity epitomised her reign. She was a continuous figure, both in this country and around the world, who managed to exercise a calm and steadying influence over our country, even its toughest times.</p>
    <p pid="b677.0/4">Rochester and Strood was blessed by many visits from Her Majesty over the years. I am immensely proud of our royal history and the links we have with our late Queen. She made her first visit to Rochester with King George VI in 1938, when they visited the Short Brothers aircraft works. That was followed by a visit to the Historic Dockyard Chatham in 1942. I hope that I am right in saying that she liked what she saw in those early visits before her accession, inspiring many trips in the following years.</p>
    <p pid="b677.0/5">In her role as its Colonel-in-Chief, she inspected the Corps of Royal Engineers at Brompton barracks in 1968, during one of her many visits there. She also opened the Royal Engineers Museum in 1987. She made her final visit in 2016 to celebrate the 300th anniversary of the corps, and it was the greatest honour of my life to meet her on that occasion.</p>
    <p pid="b677.0/6">I felt nervous, like everyone else meeting the Queen for the first time, and after overcoming the first hurdle of getting my curtsy right, I moved on to the next step of meeting her: the handshake. There I was, just over a year into being an MP, standing in front of Her Majesty, who had just turned 90, worrying about the damage that I could cause her hand should I grip too hard. I could not have been more wrong: I had failed to appreciate how years of experience had left Her Majesty skilled in  administering a handshake. With her great smile and the twinkle in her eye that so many have spoken about, she took my hand firmly, and released it before I could even take a moment.</p>
    <p pid="b677.0/7">The barracks were not the only place that the Queen had visited in Rochester. She went to Rochester cathedral, and she even took a trip to our great Isle of Grain oil refinery in 1955. Following her 1942 visit to the Historic Dockyard Chatham in 1942, she returned to the site in 1984, when she was able to see the redevelopment proposal for the closed Chatham dockyards on St Mary’s island.</p>
    <p pid="b677.0/8">Those are a few examples highlighting how committed and dedicated the Queen was to her people. She was totally devoted to the British people throughout her reign, and the hundreds of thousands of people who met her felt at ease. Her absence will be felt around the world. My thoughts and prayers are with her family. I know that King Charles III has the support of Rochester and all the good people to lead this country into a new era. God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.678.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.678.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.678.0" speakername="Ellie Reeves" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25681" colnum="678" time="14:47:00" url="">
    <p pid="b678.0/1">This is not just a time of national mourning; our grief is shared the world over, a testament to our Queen’s service and the impact she had. For seven decades, she selflessly dedicated her life to service. She was icon who meant so much to us all and who, at times, we felt we would never lose. So long was her service that her presence was sewn into the very fabric of our society, guiding our country above the fray of politics. Her unrivalled commitment and experience helped to lead our nation and keep it steady, no matter the political turbulence. In her quiet way, she symbolised the commitment, selflessness and humility that we expect from our leaders.</p>
    <p pid="b678.0/2">The progress that we saw globally in technology, culture and politics during her reign is unparalleled in history, but as an ever-present matriarch throughout, she assured us as the world changed exponentially. It is truly sad that we have now lost her. Although my words today cannot do justice to a life of such dedication, the outpouring of tributes the world over is a testament to her place in our lives. Now, our thoughts are with her family as they mourn; we all send them our condolences.</p>
    <p pid="b678.0/3">In my constituency of Lewisham West and Penge, we mourn her, too. In June, we came together across the constituency to hold platinum jubilee parties. Neighbours came together for the first time since the pandemic, children played in the street, and people made new friends—all in her name.</p>
    <p pid="b678.0/4">I was proud to help to organise my jubilee street party. My seven-year-old son declared it the “best day ever”, and we raised more than £800 for our local food bank. One of my earliest childhood memories was seeing the Queen as she visited the pioneering St Christopher’s Hospice in my constituency. Her support, and that of the royal family, made such a huge difference to its work. I know that I speak on behalf of everyone in my constituency when I say thank you, Your Majesty, for everything—the service, selflessness and humility. Queen Elizabeth II went above the call of duty, and for that, we will always be grateful.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.679.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.679.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.679.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.679.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.680.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.680.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.681.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.681.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.682.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.682.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.683.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.683.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.684.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.684.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.684.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.684.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.685.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.685.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.686.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.686.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.687.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.687.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.688.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.688.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.689.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.689.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.689.0" speakername="Gillian Keegan" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25670" colnum="689" time="15:29:00" url="">
    <p pid="b689.0/1">Thank you for calling me to speak in this debate, Madam Deputy Speaker. I start by sending my heartfelt condolences to His Majesty the King and the entire royal family and royal household.</p>
    <p pid="b689.0/2">I rise today to express the love, gratitude and respect that all those who live in the Chichester constituency have for our late Queen. In all parts of the country, and indeed the Commonwealth, our late Queen has touched every generation. Our young still have fresh memories of planting saplings to mark the recent platinum jubilee, forming the Queen’s green canopy, which like her reign will live on for decades. Those of us a little older remember the street parties for her silver jubilee and still treasure the mugs and the memories—memories that remind us what it means to be British and of our unique traditions. In no other country anywhere in the world does the whole population celebrate by sitting in the middle of the street, usually in the rain, eating sponge cake—unique and highly differentiated.</p>
    <p pid="b689.0/3">Her late Majesty visited my constituency several times to offer support to the Chichester Festival Theatre. Her first visit was with His Royal Highness Prince Philip for the inaugural season in 1962, and they came back again in 1964 for a performance of “Othello” with Lord Olivier and Dame Maggie Smith. It was during her most recent visit that I had the incredible honour of meeting Her late Majesty. Growing up in Knowsley gives you many life stills, but a proper curtsy was not one of them, so after much more practice than I care to admit, I found myself awaiting introduction, placed between our bishop and our chief constable, who reassuringly were both as nervous as I was. As the Queen entered the room, as everyone has said, we were immediately struck by her smiling eyes. As I was introduced, she immediately smiled and said, “How long have you been the Member of Parliament for Chichester?” On hearing my reply—I had been elected just a few months earlier in 2017—she shot back, “Ah—you’re a snapper!” She was of course referring to the snap general election. She then asked me how it was all going, and I had to be truthful and admit it was not going all that well. She replied kindly, “Good luck. I think you may need it.” With experience comes wisdom. My brief introduction and the subsequent lunch with our late Queen is a memory I will treasure for ever.</p>
    <p pid="b689.0/4">The late Queen is an extraordinary role model for all of us, but she had marvellous role models in her parents. They had seen our country through the perils of the second world war, and her father had even seen action at the battle of Jutland in 1916. On the death of her father, Queen Elizabeth sent a message to her first  Prime Minister, Winston Churchill, which was read to this House on <phrase class="date" code="2022-02-11">11 February</phrase> 1952. In it, she said that her father</p>
    <p pid="b689.0/5" class="indent" pwmotiontext="yes">“had set before me an example of selfless dedication which I resolved, with God’s help, to follow.”</p>
    <p pid="b689.0/6">I think we may all conclude that she honoured her promise to the British people and met it in full. On behalf of everyone in the Chichester constituency, I want to say thank you, for everything. God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.690.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.690.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.690.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.690.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.691.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.691.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.692.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.692.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.692.0" speakername="Alok Sharma" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/24902" colnum="692" time="15:42:00" url="">
    <p pid="b692.0/1">I rise to pay tribute on behalf of my constituents and myself to our late, great Queen Elizabeth. The Queen was a comforting constant through our lifetimes. She was indeed a unique beacon of wisdom, grace, kindness and courage at the head of our country and the Commonwealth for seven decades. She was the rock we turned to as a nation, in times of uncertainty and sadness, and when we celebrated occasions of national joy. Now our great Queen has gone, leaving a void in all our lives. As we mourn, our hearts go out to her family, as they grieve in their profound loss.</p>
    <p pid="b692.0/2">The Queen’s was, by any measure, the most extraordinary of lives. She touched the lives of countless other people across the world. The first time I saw the Queen in person was as an excited 10-year-old, lined-up with others along the Bath Road in Reading during the silver jubilee celebrations, all of us clutching and waving our miniature Union flags as her car sped past. We only got a fleeting glimpse of Her Majesty, but we talked excitedly about the occasion for days afterwards. Such was the reaction she inspired, in world leaders and school children alike.</p>
    <p pid="b692.0/3">The first time I got to meet the Queen properly was in 2014, when she came to open formally the magnificently rebuilt Reading train station. I can tell you, Madam Deputy Speaker, I felt the same schoolboy excitement of 37 years earlier at the prospect of meeting Her Majesty. And this time I got to shake her hand. I will always cherish that moment, and a photograph of that occasion—of the Queen smiling that famous radiant  smile—is nestled among photographs of my family in our home. Other Members have already described the trepidation that is felt during the ceremony in which a Member joins the Privy Council and collects the seal of office as a Secretary of State—the worry about kneeling on those pesky footstools! But her Majesty would always be a kind, calming influence, and she had a unique ability to make one feel at ease. Other Members have already described the trepidation that is felt during the ceremony in which a Member joins the Privy Council and collects the seal of office as a Secretary of State—the worry about kneeling on those pesky footstools! But her Majesty would always be a kind, calming influence, and she had a unique ability to make one feel at ease.</p>
    <p pid="b692.0/4">We all know that the Queen and the royal family have championed many causes, and one of those is protecting our environment and planet. The Queen was sadly not able to attend COP26 in person as she had intended, but she was kind enough to share a message with world leaders, acknowledging her pride in the leading role played by Prince Philip, Prince Charles—now our King—and Prince William in encouraging people to protect our precious planet. Ending her remarks, she said:</p>
    <p pid="b692.0/5" class="indent" pwmotiontext="yes">“I, for one, hope that this conference will be one of those rare occasions where everyone will have the chance to rise above the politics of the moment, and achieve true statesmanship.</p>
    <p pid="b692.0/6" class="indent" pwmotiontext="yes">It is the hope of many that the legacy of this summit—written in the history books yet to be printed—will describe you as the leaders who did not pass up the opportunity; and that you answered the call of those future generations.”</p>
    <p pid="b692.0/7">That history is still to be written, and I hope and pray that the leaders of today, here in our own country and across the world, will heed the Queen’s wise words.</p>
    <p pid="b692.0/8">Now, of course, we have a new monarch, King Charles III, a long-standing leader in the fight against climate change. Through my work over the past few years on the COP26 agenda, I have had the privilege of supporting the work of King Charles’s sustainable markets initiative. He is a great man, and he will be a great monarch, with the same instinctive understanding of his people and what matters to them as his mother. God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.693.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.693.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.694.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.694.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.695.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.695.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.695.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.695.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.696.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.696.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.696.0" speakername="Sarah Owen" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25823" colnum="696" time="15:58:00" url="">
    <p pid="b696.0/1">I rise to pay tribute to Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II on behalf of my constituents in Luton North.</p>
    <p pid="b696.0/2">Our country has lost its Queen, and a family have lost their cherished mother, grandmother and great-grandmother. My thoughts are with the royal family during this immense time of loss and with the people mourning the death of the Sovereign who played such a pivotal role in their lives for so many years. Many will have sadly experienced the painful hole left after the death of the head of a family—a matriarch—and they will know the emptiness that echoes through the generations because a loved one is no longer there, but they will also know the fullness of a lifetime of lessons and devotion—those things never leave us.</p>
    <p pid="b696.0/3">Since news of her death, there have been displays of affection for the Queen across Luton North, but especially from younger generations. Yesterday morning, students at Lea Manor High School lined up outside school to pay their respects, Luton Sixth Form College fell silent in remembrance, there was time for reflective prayer at  Cardinal Newman Catholic School and the headteacher at Chalk Hill Academy addressed students and staff about the need to mourn, but also to honour and celebrate the Queen’s life.</p>
    <p pid="b696.0/4">What better place to honour significant occasions than in Luton. Indeed, Her late Majesty chose Luton to mark a very significant life event, celebrating her honeymoon with Prince Philip in Luton Hoo.</p>
    <p pid="b696.0/5">They say that some things cannot be fixed but can only be carried, and the Queen was the master of carrying on. Whether it was during the second world war, at times of national crisis or, most recently, during the pandemic, the Queen was the epitome of the British phrase, “Keep calm and carry on”—easy to say, but often harder to do, especially during times of grief. I understand that her Christian faith was a driver in that, because she was never shy about her beliefs and how they motivated her service. I know that churches, mosques and temples in my diverse constituency will be keeping the royal family and the country in their prayers during this period of mourning. Sundon Park Baptist Church has opened a book of condolence, and I know that many others will be doing the same.</p>
    <p pid="b696.0/6">The Queen came to power when the nation was recovering from the aftermath of war. The King comes to power at a time when the world is also recovering and facing many challenges. In 2002, during her Christmas broadcast, the Queen spoke words that are just as relevant today, nearly 20 years on:</p>
    <p pid="b696.0/7" class="indent" pwmotiontext="yes">“Our modern world places such heavy demands on our time and attention that the need to remember our responsibilities to others is greater than ever.”</p>
    <p pid="b696.0/8">Wise, wise words. We do not have to be staunch royalists to appreciate that, in every sense, this is truly the end of an era and the beginning of another. Rest in peace, Your Majesty.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.697.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.697.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.698.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.698.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.698.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.698.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.698.1" speakername="David Duguid" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25664" colnum="698" time="16:06:00" url="">
    <p pid="b698.1/1">I rise with humility and sadness on behalf of myself and the people of Banff and Buchan to pay tribute to Her late Majesty the Queen. I also offer my condolences to King  Charles III and the royal family, as we remember that they have lost a mother, a grandmother and a great-grandmother.</p>
    <p pid="b698.1/2">For most of us, Her Majesty has always been a continuing and reassuring presence. From the ashes of the second world war to the covid-19 pandemic in more recent years, she has been there providing reassurance and inspiration to people right across our United Kingdom. She has also been a much-admired and loved figure across the Commonwealth, but also right around the world.</p>
    <p pid="b698.1/3">Sadly, unlike many others in this place, I never had the opportunity to meet the Queen. However, given that I have grown up and lived in, and now represent in this place, one of three constituencies in Aberdeenshire, it will perhaps come as no surprise that I know a fair few people who have had the privilege not only of meeting the Queen, but of actually knowing her. Listening to the tributes from right hon. and hon. Members over the last two days, I recognise the warmth and affection in the stories of those who knew her.</p>
    <p pid="b698.1/4">We have all heard how well Her Majesty could make people feel at ease, whether in a formal or a social setting. That was not just a matter of decorum or of being a nice and kind person, which of course she very much was. She somehow knew—she somehow had this sixth sense or superpower that told her—precisely what action she needed to take to make that one individual feel at ease.</p>
    <p pid="b698.1/5">As a Member of Parliament, the closest I ever got to the Queen was in the peers lobby, watching the state opening of Parliament on a screen. Before I was elected, however, Her Majesty was at the Turriff agricultural show in my hometown in 2014, on the occasion of the show’s 150th anniversary. On that occasion, I was able to get as close to the Queen as I find myself now to my hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25593" name="Robert Courts">the Member for Witney (Robert Courts)</phrase>. I found myself in the adoring crowd through which Her Majesty was moving so gracefully, as she always did. She was engaging with everyone, as she did, with that famous smile and twinkling eye we have heard so much about in the last two days—a smile with which we have all become very familiar and which we will always remember.</p>
    <p pid="b698.1/6">The organisers of the Turriff show whom the Queen met that day were moved by her humility, warmth and humour, not to mention her expert knowledge of the livestock and animals on display—horses, of course, being a particularly passion for Her Majesty, as they are for her daughter, the Princess Royal, who returned to visit the show earlier this year. The people of Turriff will remember fondly the visit of Her late Majesty, as will the people of Fraserburgh, which she visited in 1992 to celebrate the town’s 400th anniversary, and of Macduff and Banff, which she visited on a launch from the Royal Yacht Britannia in 1961.</p>
    <p pid="b698.1/7">In Scotland, we saw the Queen at her most relaxed and happy, particularly on her regular visits to her much-loved Balmoral in west Aberdeenshire. We have heard stories from her stays there, including from former Prime Ministers who had the joy of being driven around the Balmoral estate by the Queen herself in a Land  Rover. I know that it will have been a comfort to her and her family that she spent her last days in the place that she loved so much.</p>
    <p pid="b698.1/8">The United Kingdom, the Commonwealth and the world will come together in the coming days to mourn the passing of a great—perhaps the greatest—world leader. As we reflect on her long life and reign of loyal service, we also remember fondly her compassion, humour and warmth. She continues to be in all our hearts. May Her late Majesty Queen Elizabeth II rest in peace. God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.700.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.700.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.700.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.700.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.701.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.701.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.702.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.702.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.703.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.703.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.704.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.704.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.705.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.705.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.706.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.706.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.707.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.707.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.707.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.707.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.708.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.708.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.708.0" speakername="Stephanie Peacock" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25617" colnum="708" time="16:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b708.0/1">It is an honour to rise today to pay tribute to Her late Majesty Queen Elizabeth II. The whole country, the people of Barnsley, and millions across the Commonwealth and around the world are all mourning the loss of Britain’s longest-reigning monarch. I express my sadness, and I give my condolences and those of the people of Barnsley East to our new King and to our royal family. Anyone who knows me knows I am a strong supporter of our constitutional monarchy—I am a proud royalist—but I have been struck by how both those who share my view  and those who hold the opposite one are unified in admiration for our late Queen’s service, commitment and duty. Across the country, there is a profound sense of loss.</p>
    <p pid="b708.0/2">Queen Elizabeth II was part of that incredible generation of women—the most prominent of them my grandmother’s generation—who lived through, served in and survived the second world war, at a time when attitudes to women were very different. She perfectly understood the role of a constitutional monarch, public service and duty. She knew it was not her job to solve the problems of the day—that falls to us in this place—but she often spoke to our nation at times of peril, danger and division, delivering a message of comfort and unity. For me, most notably, in the wake of the horrific 9/11 terrorist attacks in 2001, she said:</p>
    <p pid="b708.0/3" class="indent" pwmotiontext="yes">“Grief is the price we pay for love.”</p>
    <p pid="b708.0/4">We draw on that sentiment today at a time of profound national sadness and mourning.</p>
    <p pid="b708.0/5">Members across the House have rightly spoken of how our Queen Elizabeth has been a constant in our lives in an ever-changing world—in difficult times and in happier ones. In 1977, she had been on the throne for a quarter of a century when she visited Barnsley as part of her silver jubilee celebrations. Our town was built on coal, and when she visited in 1954 she was given a commemorative piece to mark the occasion. I know the people of Barnsley celebrated then as they mourn today.</p>
    <p pid="b708.0/6">The late Queen had a unique ability to unite us all, and today we are united in our grief. As the poet laureate, Yorkshireman Simon Armitage, wrote in his collection “Queenhood” to mark the platinum jubilee:</p>
    <p pid="b708.0/7" class="indent" pwmotiontext="yes">“For generations we will not know such majesty.”</p>
    <p pid="b708.0/8">As our Elizabethan age closes, those words ring true. As we mourn her loss, as we celebrate her life and as we thank her for her service, we say rest in peace, and we say God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.709.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.709.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.710.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.710.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.710.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.710.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.711.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.711.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.712.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.712.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.712.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.712.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.712.1" speakername="Jack Brereton" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25698" colnum="712" time="17:00:00" url="">
    <p pid="b712.1/1">So many people here in the UK, in my city of Stoke-on-Trent and across the Commonwealth will be feeling a great deal of loss and sadness, which is hard to express. The Queen visited Stoke-on-Trent on a number of occasions, first in 1949. People across our city will be mourning her loss. Our heartfelt condolences go out to His Majesty and the King and the entire royal family.</p>
    <p pid="b712.1/2">Few alive today can remember a time without Her Majesty the Queen; for many it will be difficult to imagine a life without her. Over 70 years of dutiful service, her constancy and strength have guided our great nation and 14 other Commonwealth realms, each of which she cared for very deeply. Over that time, the world has changed almost unrecognisably, but she was always there to offer stability to us in times of great change, and reassurance in times of crisis. Even in these final few years of her life, despite declining health and the loss of her deeply beloved Philip, at the age of 96 she continued to perform her important duties as our Head of State.</p>
    <p pid="b712.1/3">Just as His Royal Highness the Duke of Edinburgh was Her Majesty’s strength and stay, she was our strength and stay. That is how she will be remembered. She was our longest-reigning monarch and probably our greatest, if not one of the greatest leaders that the world has ever seen. One of her greatest abilities was to remain above politics, bridging divides, whether political, across communities or generational.</p>
    <p pid="b712.1/4">Along with thousands of others who had the chance, I was lucky enough with my wife Laura to attend one of the Queen’s numerous garden parties at Buckingham Palace a few years ago. It was a day that I will never forget, I am sure along with all those who had that chance. Many never had the chance to meet the Queen directly, but there is still a great feeling of loss and sadness. She was a significant part of our lives. She was loved by all of us. That was clear to see in the great deal of affection and respect shown to Her Majesty in the huge outpouring of support earlier this year during the platinum jubilee celebrations, just as we now see the massive expression of sympathy around the world.</p>
    <p pid="b712.1/5">We will now join in mourning her loss and supporting our new King. I know from meeting him previously on a number of occasions that, following his mother’s example, he will do all that he can to support our great nation, and that he has a great deal of affection for my city of Stoke-on-Trent.</p>
    <p pid="b712.1/6">Let us never forget our Elizabeth the Great. She is now at peace, reunited with her beloved Philip. Her achievements and memory will live on. God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.713.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.713.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.713.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.713.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.714.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.714.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.715.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.715.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.716.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.716.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.716.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.716.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.716.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.716.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.716.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.716.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.717.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.717.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.718.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.718.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.719.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.719.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.720.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.720.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.720.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.720.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.721.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.721.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.722.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.722.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.723.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.723.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.724.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.724.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.724.0" speakername="Daniel Kawczynski" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/11817" colnum="724" time="17:46:00" url="">
    <p pid="b724.0/1">I rise on behalf of the people of Shrewsbury and the surrounding Shropshire villages to pay tribute to Her Majesty. When I met Her Majesty at Buckingham Palace, she looked at me and immediately started to tease me—to rib me mercilessly—about the difference in height, she being 5 feet 2 inches and me being 6 feet 9 inches. Of course, that immediately broke the ice. I was so nervous at meeting my sovereign for the first  time, and it was so good to have that joke at the start of our interaction. Later on in the evening, she was standing at one end of the room and I was at the other end. In front of everybody, she continued teasing me with a gesture about the difference in height.</p>
    <p pid="b724.0/2">The most important thing that happened that evening, however, was that the Queen realised that I was the only Polish-born British Member of Parliament. She started to talk to me about her pride in the contribution of Polish fighter pilots during the second world war. She referenced the fact that the Polish 303 squadron shot down more enemy aircraft in the battle of Britain than any other squadron did, and she paid tribute to the extraordinary contribution of Polish mathematicians and cryptographers in helping to break the enigma code at Bletchley, and to the forces that joined the British Eighth Army in north Africa and at Monte Cassino. Of course, my heart melted.</p>
    <p pid="b724.0/3">Being the only Polish-born British Member of Parliament and listening to our sovereign outlining her pride in the Polish contribution, and talking about how her father had outlined to her his pride in it, is something that I will always remember. She reigned so successfully because she used emotional intelligence, and emotional intelligence was her driving force. The communist regime in the country of my birth has been consigned to the ash heap of history because it ruled through fear, intimidation and the secret police. It is gone, whereas Her Majesty’s memory is eternal because of the love and kindness that she showed us all.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.725.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.725.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.726.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.726.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.726.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.726.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.727.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.727.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.728.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.728.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.729.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.729.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.729.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.729.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.730.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.730.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.730.0" speakername="Jack Lopresti" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/24716" colnum="730" time="18:09:00" url="">
    <p pid="b730.0/1">Sadly, I never met the Queen. It was something I had always hoped to do. However, as for most people in our country and the Commonwealth, she was always a positive presence in my life.</p>
    <p pid="b730.0/2">We remember that Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II was not only our Head of State and the mother of our nation, but had the same responsibilities and duties for the peoples of our dependent sovereign territories—faraway places such as the Falkland Islands—and for the Governments and peoples of the Commonwealth nations around the world. That was brought home to me in an amazing way when I was chairman of the all-party group on Gibraltar.</p>
    <p pid="b730.0/3">Gibraltar National Day is today, <phrase class="date" code="2022-09-10">10 September</phrase>, when Gibraltar celebrates its unique identity and its Britishness. Normally, there is a huge rally in Casemates Square, which is right in the middle of Gibraltar. It is a fantastic occasion, when the whole place is festooned with Union flags and the red and white of the Gibraltar flag. Today, the celebrations have been postponed until next year, and the proclamation of King Charles III was shown on the screens in Casemates Square. Fabian Picardo, the Chief Minister, spoke yesterday of a “cloud of sorrow” over the Rock. The Royal Gibraltar Regiment had a 96-gun salute.</p>
    <p pid="b730.0/4">In happier times, in the diamond jubilee year of 2012, the National Day rally had a huge picture of the Queen, and every platform speaker expressed thanks and appreciation for Her Majesty’s service and spoke of their pride in their Britishness and in their Queen, referring to the fact that she had visited Gibraltar. On the platform that day, Fabian used a phrase that I had not heard before but that encapsulates how the Queen was a great unifier of many different peoples and nations. He said that the people of Gibraltar, other sovereign territories and the Commonwealth are all part of the “great British family”—even more so in Gibraltar, a small piece of rock, with a real melting pot of different religions and cultures, within physical sight of the north African coast. Everyone was united on that day, with an outpouring of love, pride and appreciation for our monarch. It reminded me of that old Latin quote, “civis romanus sum”—“I am a Roman citizen”—which one could be, from Africa to northern Britannia, regardless of one’s place of birth or religion.</p>
    <p pid="b730.0/5">Yesterday evening, I rushed back to my constituency to attend a service at St Peter’s church in Filton. The congregation was told by the Rev. Lizzie Gregory that it was not a service of commemoration—that will come—but a time for the community to come together, support one other, grieve together and give thanks. It was a wonderful service and it was great to see so many people there. Most had come on foot from nearby. I could sense the pride, depth of emotion and the community supporting one another.</p>
    <p pid="b730.0/6">I do not normally quote French Heads of State, unless they were born in Corsica, but President Macron’s comments on the passing of the Queen sum up how we and the rest of the world saw her:</p>
    <p pid="b730.0/7" class="indent" pwmotiontext="yes">“To you, she was your Queen. To us, she was The Queen. She will be with all of us forever.”</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.731.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.731.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.732.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.732.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.732.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.732.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.733.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.733.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.734.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.734.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.734.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.734.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.735.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.735.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.736.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.736.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.737.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.737.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.737.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.737.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.738.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.738.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.739.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.739.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.740.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.740.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.740.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.740.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.740.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.740.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.740.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.740.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.741.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.741.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.741.0" speakername="Jonathan Gullis" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25898" colnum="741" time="18:54:00" url="">
    <p pid="b741.0/1">It is with great sadness that I stand today, on behalf of the people of Stoke-on-Trent North, Kidsgrove and Talke, to share in our collective grief at the loss of the grandmother of the nation, Her late Majesty, Queen Elizabeth II. Like the constituencies of many across this House, Stoke-on-Trent North, Kidsgrove and Talke was blessed to host Her late Majesty the Queen on a few occasions. This went all the way back to 1949, when the then Princess visited the potteries, in the mother town of Burslem. She returned in 1955, visiting 30,000 excited schoolchildren at the old home of Stoke City football club, the Victoria Ground. She visited again in 1999, when she came to the Dudson Centre, meeting members of the touring Hallé orchestra.</p>
    <p pid="b741.0/2">My right hon. Friend <phrase class="honfriend" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10999" name="Boris Johnson">the Member for Uxbridge and South Ruislip (Boris Johnson)</phrase> was right when he said that we allowed ourselves to believe Her late Majesty the Queen to be eternal. In preparation for this speech, I reflected on some words from the famous Stoke-on-Trent author Arnold Bennett, who said</p>
    <p pid="b741.0/3" class="indent" pwmotiontext="yes">“We shall never have more time. We have, and have always had, all the time there is.”</p>
    <p pid="b741.0/4">Bennett is right, in that we shall no longer have Her late Majesty the Queen as a physical presence in our lives—I have tried to explain that to my daughter Amelia, who, only on Tuesday, was on FaceTime to me while I was lucky enough sit here in this Palace of Westminster and was saying, “Daddy meet the Queen”—but Her late Majesty’s legacy will continue to live on forever, in generations yet to come. Her dedication to public service and duty, her national pride and her unwavering personal faith provide lessons for us all to pass down to our children and grandchildren, enabling us to help support her successor, our King, in taking us forward into the future, unsure of what lies ahead but collectively empowering us to stand shoulder to shoulder, undeterred in our love and belief in our United Kingdom. The people of Stoke-on-Trent North, Kidsgrove and Talke, including me, give our heartfelt condolences to His Majesty King Charles III and his family at this time, for they have lost not only their Queen, but a mother, grandmother and great-grandmother. As we pray that Her late Majesty the Queen lies in eternal peace and happiness, myself and the people of Stoke-on-Trent North, Kidsgrove and Talke wish to bear our true faith and allegiance to His Majesty King Charles III, as she would have wanted. God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.742.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.742.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.743.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.743.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.743.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.743.1" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.743.1" speakername="Christopher Chope" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/10103" colnum="743" time="19:01:00" url="">
    <p pid="b743.1/1">My constituents and I thank His Majesty the King for his words of comfort and reassurance following today’s proclamation of accession as sovereign. We send His Majesty and the whole royal family our deepest condolences on the death of Her Majesty.</p>
    <p pid="b743.1/2">The second Elizabethan age has received many references in the last day and a half of debate. Christchurch probably has more people than any other constituency who can remember the beginning of the second Elizabethan age, in 1952, and I am among those privileged to have lived throughout the late Queen’s 70-year reign. I first saw her at her coronation in 1953, when my parents were invited to watch it on a friend’s black-and-white television—I think it was the first time I had ever seen a television.</p>
    <p pid="b743.1/3">I have been lucky enough to meet Her late Majesty on several occasions, first at an investiture in 1982 and last at an investiture in 2018, but the meeting to which I shall allude took place when I was asked by the Secretary of State for Transport to host the occasion when Her Majesty opened the Queen Elizabeth II bridge across the Thames, linking the two parts of the M25. As a junior Minister, I was tremendously nervous, but Her Majesty put me at my ease. We had a long private  conversation about the bridge, its construction and its funding, and I remember assuring her that the tolls would be lifted as soon as the bridge was paid for. I am pleased to say that Her Majesty kept her counsel on that, as today the tolls are still there even through the bridge has been paid for several times over. I remember that occasion distinctly.</p>
    <p pid="b743.1/4">So also do I remember the occasion when Her late Majesty attended the 80th birthday party of Margaret Thatcher. The way she showed her support and encouragement to Margaret Thatcher on that occasion was really moving, because she was not in the best of health. That is an example of the way in which Her late Majesty rose to the occasion. She was not doing something party political—I think Tony Blair was there as well—but her compassion showed through to all of us who had the privilege to be present.</p>
    <p pid="b743.1/5">The Queen encapsulated and exemplified all those qualities that make our nation the envy of the world, and make us so proud to be British. The second Elizabethan age, which has drawn to a close this week, will be revered for centuries to come. Weren’t we lucky to be part of it?</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.744.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.744.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.745.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.745.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.745.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.745.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.746.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.746.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.747.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.747.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.748.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.748.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.748.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.748.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.749.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.749.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.750.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.750.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.750.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.750.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.751.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.751.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.752.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.752.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.753.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.753.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.754.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.754.0" matchtype="changes"/>
<speech id="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.754.0" speakername="Matt Vickers" type="Start Speech" person_id="uk.org.publicwhip/person/25853" colnum="754" time="19:45:00" url="">
    <p pid="b754.0/1">It is an honour to rise on behalf of the people of Stockton South to offer our deepest condolences to the royal family and to pay tribute to our longest-serving and greatest monarch. Since 1952, our nation has changed beyond all recognition. The people of 1952 would recognise little of modern society, with the exception of one thing: Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II. For 70 years, our gracious sovereign lady has provided stability, continuity and a sense of reassurance to millions across this nation and to billions across the world.</p>
    <p pid="b754.0/2">The Queen has a special place in the hearts of the people of Stockton. During the jubilee weekend, we saw communities come together with huge celebrations in my part of the world. Many shared their stories of the Queen’s visits to Stockton in 1956, 1977 and, most recently, 2012, when she opened our white water course.</p>
    <p pid="b754.0/3">The Queen was a lady of small stature but huge personality and presence. She was someone every world leader wanted to be seen with, including 15 Prime Ministers, 14 Presidents of the United States and many other leaders. She saw them come and she saw them go. While they were able to step down, walk away and retire, Her Majesty never had such a luxury. The vow she made in 1947 to dedicate her whole life to service was as true then as it was at the end. Her Majesty showed that age is but a number.</p>
    <p pid="b754.0/4">For me, the Queen was basically Britannia—a titan in her own right, a proud defender of the United Kingdom and the Commonwealth, and our true strength and stay. Not only did she see her nation engage in combat over the seven decades of her reign but she herself saw active service in world war two. That image of Her Majesty behind the wheel of a wagon in her uniform is one that can make us only proud—proud of her and proud to be British.</p>
    <p pid="b754.0/5">Today, in every city, every town, every village and every street of our nation, we all mourn the loss of our Queen, our guiding light, our nation’s rock—the best of Britain. We must never forget the incredible example Her Majesty set. On behalf of the people of Stockton South, I offer her our thanks for her incredible life of service. God bless Her Majesty. May she rest in peace and rise in glory. God save the King.</p>
</speech>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.754.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.754.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.755.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.755.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.756.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.756.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.756.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.756.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.757.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.757.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.758.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.758.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.759.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.759.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.760.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.760.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.761.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.761.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.761.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.761.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.762.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.762.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.762.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.762.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.764.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.764.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.764.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.764.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.765.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.765.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.765.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.765.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.766.0" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.766.0" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.766.1" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.766.1" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.766.2" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.766.2" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.766.3" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.766.3" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
<gidredirect oldgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10b.766.4" newgid="uk.org.publicwhip/debate/2022-09-10c.766.4" matchtype="perfectmatch"/>
</publicwhip>

